Porter Family Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Porter Family Papers 1811-1881
MSS53041
Porter family
100 items
2 containers
.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Naval officers and authors. Papers of David Porter (1780-1843) and his son, David Dixon Porter (1813-1891) relating to their naval careers and families.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Goff, Nathan, 1843-1920--Correspondence.; Hambleton, Samuel, 1777-1851--Correspondence.; Hunt, William H. (William Henry), 1823-1883--Correspondence.; McCorkle, James P.--Correspondence.; Porter family.; Porter, David D. (David Dixon), 1813-1891. David D. Porter papers. 1861-1881.; Porter, David, 1780-1843. David Porter papers. 1811-1841.; Porter, Evelina Anderson, 1790-1871--Correspondence.; Porter, George Ann Patterson--Correspondence.; Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872--Correspondence.; Thompson, Richard W. (Richard Wigginton), 1809-1900--Correspondence.; Walker, George W.--Correspondence.
Organizations
Essex (Frigate); Mexico. Armada.
Places
Minorca (Spain)--Social life and customs.; New Orleans (La.)--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Occupations
Authors.; Naval officers.
Provenance
The Porter Family Papers were deposited in the Library of Congress by the Naval Historical Foundation in 1949. The deposit was converted to a gift by the foundation in 1998.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Porter family are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
David Porter
Date Event
1780, Feb. 1 Born, Boston, Mass.
1798 Appointed midshipman, United States Navy Duty on Constellation (frigate)
1799 Duty on Experiment (schooner), West India Squadron
1801 Duty on Enterprize (schooner), Tripolitan War
1803 Duty on Philadelphia (frigate), Tripolitan War
1803 1805 Prisoner of war, Tripoli
1808 Married Evelina Anderson
1808 1810 Commandant, New Orleans Naval Station
1811 1814 Commanded Essex (frigate)
1812 Promoted to captain
1815 Published Journal of a Cruise Made to the Pacific Ocean. Philadelphia: Bradford & Inskeep
1815 1823 Commissioner, Navy Board
1823 1825 Commander in chief, West India Squadron
1825 Published An Exposition of the Facts and Circumstances Which Justified the Expedition to Foxardo. Washington: Printed by Davis & Force
1826 Resigned from United States Navy
1826 1829 Commander in chief, Mexican Navy
1830 Appointed United States consul general, Algiers
1831 Appointed United States chargé d’affaires, Turkey
1835 Published Constantinople and Its Environs. New York: Harper. 2 vols.
1839 Appointed United States Minister, Turkey
1843, Mar. 3 Died, Pera, Constantinople
David Dixon Porter
Date Event
1813, June 8 Born, Chester, Pa.
1827 Appointed midshipman, Mexican Navy
1829 Appointed midshipman, United States Navy Duty on Constellation (frigate), Mediterranean Station
1839 Married George Ann Patterson
1842 Duty on Congress (frigate)
1847 Duty on Spitfire (side-wheel gunboat)
1849 Commanded Panama (steamer)
1850 1853 Commanded Georgia (steamer)
1855 Commanded Supply (ship)
1857 Duty at the Portsmouth Navy Yard, Portsmouth, Va.
1861 Commanded Powhatan (side-wheel steamer)
1863 Commander, Mississippi Squadron Promoted to rear admiral
1864 Commander, North Atlantic Blockading Squadron
1865 1869 Superintendent, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md.
1866 Promoted to vice admiral
1866 1867 Diplomatic mission to Santo Domingo
1870 Promoted to admiral
1875 Published Memoir of Commodore David Porter. Albany, N.Y.: J. Munsell
1877 1891 Chairman, Naval Board of Inspection
1885 Published The Adventures of Harry Marline. New York: D. Appleton Published Allan Dare and Robert le Diable. New York: D. Appleton. 2 vols. Published Incidents and Anecdotes of the Civil War. New York: D. Appleton
1886 Published The Naval History of the Civil War. New York: Sherman Publishing Co.
1889 Published Arthur Merton. New York: D. Appleton
1891, Feb. 13 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of the Porter family document the careers of naval officers David Porter (1780-1843) and his son, David Dixon Porter (1813-1891). The collection spans the years 1811-1881 and consists primarily of correspondence and letterbooks. The material is organized as the papers of each man and arranged alphabetically thereunder by type of material or name of person.
Letters from David Porter to his friend Samuel Hambleton in 1811-1812 describe his command of the frigate Essex charged with protecting Atlantic coast merchantmen. In a letter dated October 19, 1812, Porter related to Hambleton that “In two or three days I sail on a long, a very long cruize [sic], our destinations and intended movements I am not at liberty to divulge, perhaps a more important cruize was never undertaken by the vessels of any nation and I have the vanity to believe that my plans for the ‘first campaign’ produced it.” Soon thereafter in early 1813, Porter took the Essex around Cape Horn to safeguard American whalers and in so doing commanded the first United States naval vessel to sail into the Pacific Ocean. Letters to his wife Evelina Anderson Porter relate details of his service as commander in chief of the Mexican Navy in 1826-1829 and of domestic affairs while living in Port Mahón on the Mediterranean island of Minorca in1830. Other recipients of letters in the file include James P. McCorkle and George W. Walker. Also included is a draft of Porter’s resignation as commander in chief of the Mexican Navy and his will dictated in San Stefano, Turkey.
Official letterbooks of David Dixon Porter from the periods 1867-1869 and 1878-1881 comprise the bulk of the collection and contain copies of letters to three secretaries of the navy, Richard W. Thompson, Nathan Goff, and William H. Hunt. A letter from Porter while in New Orleans in 1862 to his wife George Ann Porter recounted the bitterness of their southern relatives under Union occupation of that city. Other items include printed naval general orders and circulars.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is organized as the papers of each man and arranged alphabetically thereunder by type of material or name of person.
Container List
- Porter, David (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Hambleton, Samuel, 1811-1814 (Box 1)
    - McCorkle, James P., 1830 (Box 1)
    - Porter, Evelina Anderson, 1826-1830 (Box 1)
    - Walker, George W., circa 1823 (Box 1)
  - Draft of resignation from Mexican navy, circa 1829 (Box 1)
  - Will, 1841 (Box 1)
- Porter, David Dixon (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1861-1862 (Box 1)
  - General orders and circulars, North Atlantic Squadron and European Fleet, 1864-1873 (Box 1)
  - Letterbooks (Box 1)
    - 1867-1869 (Box 1)
    - 1878-1881, (2 vols.) (Box 2)